Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is כ''ה. Chaf-Hey. We
begin in the middle of כ''ו Chaf-Vav עמוד ד'. amud daled. We're
in the middle of a discussion here about in the new פרק
perek about מפלת mapelet or about women with miscarriages what constitutes a
fetus, but we have also looked very importantly this question about that
even if it is not a fetus and not טמא, tamei, but
some type of a chunk expelled from the woman's uterus, do we
say that that means that blood necessarily came out even if we
did not see it? אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא
דם, I efshar liftichat hakever belo dam, which as I told you
is very important because the גמרא Gemorah talks about it coming expelled
from the woman and the pressure and so on, very particular circumstances,
but the נודע ביהודה Noda Biyehuda applies it even to something being
inserted into the uterus from the outside, which leads to all issues
of gynecological exams, which רב משה Rav Moshe makes mostly moot by
speaking about that it only is a certain size and of the
instrument, of the width of the circumference of the instrument. But nevertheless,
this concept is an important concept in a number of practical halachic
issues. So we now return to another very important concept which related
to this. So let's take a look. It's כ''ו Chaf-Vav עמוד ב'
amud bet again, it's about exactly midway in the middle lines and
it is בעי מיניה רב ירמיה מרב זירא. Ba'ei minei Rav Yirmiyah
me-Rav Zeira. The line starts with the word מרב זירא. me-Rav Zeira.
About fifteen lines down or fifteen lines up from the middle line.
Okay, so רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah asked from רב זירא: Rav Zeira:
הרואה דם בשפופרת
מהו? Haro'ah dam beshofofert mahu? Let's say a woman sees blood in
a tube. A tube is inserted up to her cervix or up
to, you know, the inner or the outer os of the cervix
or up to the opening of the uterus, and the blood never
makes it into touches the vaginal canal. It goes straight into this
tube like there's a funnel, maybe something to catch it and out
of the body. Now this seems a little bit absurd or bizarre—not
absurd, but bizarre—but I should tell you actually that what I taught
הלכות נידה Hilchos Niddah a few years ago, one of my students
found that there actually is a device, you can market it on
the web, for women who do not want to have to deal
with other ways of dealing, you know, with their period, and it's
actually is essentially some type of a suction cup that you insert
and it actually does this, it like sucks out the blood or
funnels out the blood, so you know, and gets rid of it
all at once so you don't have to deal with it. Right,
I know, so they were—I assume for them it was more of
a hypothetical, but I'm just—but right, but it's a hypothetical that explores
certain parameters.
I would not rule out that there might not have been something.
Attempts to do
that. But the question is, though, it needs a combination because if
you just have a tube there, not all the blood is going
to go into the tube. So here the point is that the
blood that came out only went through the tube, it did not
touch the vaginal canal. A woman is considered to be a נידה
Niddah when basically—I mean there's some debate about the exact moments, but
it's assumed to be when the blood leaves the outer os of
the cervix, meaning the opening of the cervix that opens into the
vaginal canal, not the inner os which opens into the uterus. When
it leaves the outer os of the cervix into the vaginal canal.
So what happens if the blood never touched the vaginal canal, it
just went straight into this tube, what would be the הלכה? Halacha?
So the גמרא Gemorah says like this: what's the question? You'll see
how it ties to things we've been discussing. You might imagine we
talked about blood being in a little, you know, inside of the
chunk, inside of the chunk, not touching the vaginal canal, so you
can see where we're going. But let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemorah says. What's the הלכה? Halacha? בשרה אמר רחמנא ולא בשפופרת.
Bisarah amar rachmana velo beshofofert. It says blood is flowing בשרה. bisarah.
דם יהיה זובה בבשרה—flowing Dam yihiyeh zovah bivsarah in her flesh. So
maybe that means, thank you, touching her flesh, touching the the skin,
the walls of the vaginal canal, that literally in her flesh and
not in the tube. או דילמא האי בשרה מיבעי ליה שמטמא מבפנים
כמבחוץ? O dilma hai bisarah mibayei leh shematamei mibifnim kembachutz? Maybe בשרה
bisarah means, no, it's inside of her flesh even before it leaves
her body. And as we said, that's a very central law to
הלכות נידה. Hilchos Niddah. It's because of that law that we have
all these realities of בדיקות, bedikos, all these requirements and all these
questions of exactly when she became טמאה, tameiah, because she's טמאה tamei
even before it exits her body, even when it goes as I
said from the cervix to the vaginal canal. So maybe that's the
only thing it tells us but not that it actually have to
touch the skin on the inside. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so he
said back to him—רב זירא Rav Zeira responded—בשרה אמר רחמנא. Bisarah amar
rachmana. Inner flesh ולא בשפופרת. velo beshofofert. Yes, it does mean literal.
Now I should point out it's quite interesting because here you have
אמוראים Amora'im doing דרשות. drashot. Normally we only find תנאים Tanna'im doing
דרשות drashot on the פסוקים, psukim, but it is not limited to
that. And here it's here they're actually asking a practical halachic question
and answering it by a דרשה drasha that they are sort of
deciding on their own. So that's what he said: and if בשרה
מיבעי ליה שמטמא מבפנים כמבחוץ, bisarah mibayei leh shematamei mibifnim kembachutz, if
the whole point is to say that she's טמאה tameiah when it's
in her body even before the blood leaves her body, אם כן
נימא קרא, im kein neima kra, why doesn't the תורה Torah just
say... now here's the question: בבשר—in bivsar the flesh. Okay. מאי בשרה?
Mai bisarah? What, "in her flesh"? Let's say it just said בבשר
bivsar without the ה. hey. And anyway, what does it mean "in
her flesh"? That's seen as a little extra emphasis. שמע מינה תרתי.
Shma mina tarti. It has to actually touch the flesh on the
inside, it has to touch the walls of the vaginal canal. So
now, as I said, this seems to be an interesting but totally
hypothetical question. I shall give you, there's a very... practical issue that
will come out in a minute based on how we read the
continuation of the גמרא, Gemara, but I will give you one practical
example, again somewhat bizarre.
רב שלמה זלמן אויערבאך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach in a very lengthy
תשובה Teshuvah deals with the question of what's now called, sadly, עקרה
הלכתית, Akara Hilchatit, a woman who cannot become עקרה הלכתית, Akara Hilchatit,
which means halakhically barren, which is a woman that's totally fertile, but
basically because of the keeping these, waiting for the blood to stop
and then keeping seven clean days, she cannot her, you know, her
fertility period is before she becomes טהורה. Tehorah. And there's very serious
questions about how to deal with that, actually it's become a major,
major issue in the Israeli, in the, you know, in Israel the
last few years, somebody's written like a book even about it, להחזיר
עטרה ליושנה, Lahazir Atarah LeYoshnah,
about questions about under what circumstances maybe, you know, can we consider
חומרא דרבי זירא Chumra D'Rabbi Zeira for the sake of פרו ורבו?
Pru Urvu? So רב שלמה זלמן אויערבאך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach has
a very long תשובה Teshuvah about this, actually the, I believe that
the story was that his daughter had this situation, and he discusses
at great length this question about can חומרא דרבי זירא Chumra D'Rabbi
Zeira ever be waived for, for פרו ורבו Pru Urvu if it's
impossible otherwise? And he sort of goes back and forth and he
feels at the end you cannot come to that conclusion, although he,
like you can see he's clearly struggling with it. And then in
the end what he suggests for those situations is doing this solution:
putting in a type of a suction cup, not to sort of
suck it out, maybe you could, I don't know, that would get
it done quickly, have all the blood come out this way, so
the woman wouldn't be a נדה Niddah that month, and then she
would be able to, you know, have sex with her husband during
her fertile period. Whether anybody has actually ever implemented it, I don't
know. Now also's not the time to get into a lengthy discussion
about חומרא דרבי זירא, Chumra D'Rabbi Zeira, believe me we'll have plenty
of that, but I just wanted to point out that this גמרא
Gemara actually, seems bizarre this situation, but has, you know, been suggested
to be applied להלכה L'halachah under certain circumstances.
And this is רבי זירא.
Rabbi Zeira. This is רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, oh that's a good
point too, it's the same רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. Okay, so now,
but now we're going to see another way in which it becomes
very relevant, at least based on an interpretation of the סוגיא. Sugya.
So let's continue. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא אמר רבי יוחנן,
V'ha Amar Rabbi Yochanan, can you really say that that's true, that
it's only if it touches the walls of the vaginal canal? Doesn't
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say משום שמעון יוחאי, Mishum Shimon Yochai, המפלת
חתיכה, Mapeles Chaticha, if somebody, if a woman miscarries like a chunk,
something that is presumed to be not blood? So what do you,
I mean, you open it up, אם יש בה דם אגור, Im
Yesh Ba Dam Agur, טמאה, Temeiah, if there's blood collected in it
she's טמאה, Temeiah, ואם לאו טהורה, Ve'im Lav Tehorah, and if not
she's טהורה. Tehorah. And we saw yesterday some, that was even the
most lenient of a range of opinions. I mean, some say טהור
Tahor regardless, but some say even a drop of blood, even reddish.
So presumably we're saying that the stuff inside is the problematic blood,
not the chunk, only if there's blood inside, and even though it's
in this, the hollow of this chunk, right, the cavity of this
chunk, and it's not touching the vaginal canal, she's טמאה. Temeiah. So
you see the blood does not have to touch the vaginal canal,
pretty good proof, at least according to those תנאים. Tannaim. So the
answer is the following: הכי השתא. Chafi Hasha. What type of proof
is that? What are you talking about? התם דרכה של אשה לראות
דם בחתיכה. Hasam Darcha Shel Isha Lirot Dam BeChaticha. הכא אין דרכה
של אשה לראות דם בשפופרת. Hacha Ein Darcha Shel Isha Lirot Dam
Beshofre. It's natural for there to be blood, I mean it's not
natural for a woman to have these chunks come out of her
body, but it's natural for there to be blood inside of those
chunks and as opposed to the tube, it is not natural for
blood to be coming out through a tube. Now, who cares about
natural? Why should that matter? So there are two possible explanations. One
is a radical shift from what we said before: that the idea,
the problem with the tube is not the issue of touching the
walls, the problem with the tube is it's unnatural, and if blood
comes out in an unnatural way, then she's not a נדה. Niddah.
Okay, maybe actually there's a thinking that the tube even maybe caused
it to come out, but even if not, somehow that it's described
as unnatural, whereas if it's here coming out in this chunk, not
that we're saying the chunks are so common, but it's a natural
occurrence and therefore it's not an issue. That's one way of reading
it, that is not the way רש"י Rashi reads it. רש"י Rashi
consistently understands that the problem here is physically touching, and if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, דרכה של אשה לראות דם בחתיכה, Darcha Shel
Isha Lirot Dam BeChaticha, about 15 lines up from רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says, הילכך בשרה קרינא ביה, Hilkach Besarah Kerina Bei, we could
still call it in her flesh, דמין במינה לא חייץ, Demin Bemina
Lo Chayatz, which is not the גמרא's Gemara language of דרכה. Darcha.
דרכה Darcha just means it's natural. רש"י Rashi says, look, it's skin
in skin. The stuff that it's inside is also some type of
a skin or some type of thing created by the body. So
that's not considered to separate between the blood and the walls of
the vaginal canal if it's in this type of a, you know,
this type of a whatever it is, I'm trying to find a
better word than chunk. But anyway, some type of a thing that's
coming out of the body. That's not, so whereas if it's something
man-made, unnatural, a mass, that's a much better word, thank you, a
mass. If it's something man-made and unnatural, whatever, that serves as a
separation. So it's not whether it's natural for this to happen, it's
whether the thing it's in is considered to be a foreign substance,
actually that's the best word, is it a natural substance or a
foreign substance? The mass is a natural substance. The tube is a
foreign substance, and that causes a separation. Remember those two approaches, it'll
be very important as we continue. So let's take a look now
at how the גמרא Gemara concludes. Okay, לימא שופפרת תנאי. Lima Shofre
Tana'i. Maybe this question of the tube is a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, de'tanya, דתניא de'tanya the ברייתא: braita: המפלת חתיכה. hamapeles
chaticha. If a woman, you know, what's it called, expelled. Thank you,
expelled a mass. אף על פי שמלאה דם, af al pi shemele'a
dam, even if it's filled with blood, אם יש עמה דם, im
yesh ima dam, if there is
blood with it on the outside, טמאה. temei'ah. Then she's טמאה. temei'ah.
ואם לאו טהורה, v'im lav tehorah, if not she's טהורה. tehorah. So
fairly anything on the inside, even on the inside of a mass,
it's irrelevant. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: בשרה. b'sarah. There's a
verse that says this, I'm sure, in her flesh, ולא בשליא ולא
בחתיכה, v'lo b'shilya v'lo b'chaticha, not inside some type of an embryonic
sac or you know not inside of a mass. So it doesn't
matter, even if it's a natural not foreign body, if it's on
the inside it doesn't matter. It has to be touching the flesh.
So the גמרא Gemara says רבי אליעזר היינו תנא קמא. Rabbi Eliezer
hainu Tanna Kama. That's what we just said. It's not a different
opinion. Okay. אימא שרבי אליעזר אומר. eima she'Rabbi Eliezer omer. So we're
saying yes, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, this is the position of רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is sort of you know
sort of supporting this position. בשרה ולא בשליא ולא בחתיכה. b'sarah v'lo
b'shilya v'lo b'chaticha. So here you have an opinion. Blood inside something
even inside of a mass, a non-foreign body, does not make the
woman a נידה. niddah. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, the Sages say: אין
זה דם נידה אלא דם חתיכה. ein zeh dam niddah ella dam
chaticha. This blood is not נידה niddah blood, the blood inside the
mass, it is blood of this mass and it's not נידה niddah
blood at all. It's not blood of the menstrual lining. It's not
a question of is it touching the vaginal canal. The issue why
she's טהורה tehorah here is because it is not, the source of
this blood is not the uterine lining. So there's a very big
difference, right? One says even if you're getting uterine blood, it has
to touch the walls of the canal and the other says I
don't really agree with that. The only but I do agree she's
טהורה tehorah here because this is not blood, it's not uterine blood,
it's blood of the mass, but I don't agree with your whole
idea that it has to touch the walls. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the גמרא Gemara says: תנא
קמא נמי טהורי קא מטהר. Tanna Kama nami tiharu'ei ka mtahar. So
the תנא קמא Tanna Kama also says it's טהורה. tehorah. So they
both agree it's טהורה. tehorah. So what's the difference? So I've already
indicated to you. Okay they're agreeing this case is טהור tehor but
the question is why? So the גמרא Gemara is going to give
you a case where it matters. אלא דפליגי. ella de'pali'ei. Here would
be a case where they would disagree. Let's say you had this
mass and let's say this mass had, you know, crevices on the
outside of the mass and there was blood inside of those crevices.
Okay so and then it came out. What would be the story?
איכא בינייהו. ika beinaihu. That would be a way of telling the
difference of their two approaches. תנא קמא סבר: Tanna Kama savar: בשרה
ולא בשליא ולא בחתיכה, b'sarah v'lo b'shilya v'lo b'chaticha, והוא הדין לשפופרת.
v'hu hadin l'shofopheret. The first opinion is that it's a question about
being on the inside, not touching the vaginal canal. So therefore it
would not, so the flesh as opposed to you know the embryonic
sac as opposed to or the placenta as opposed to a mass
and as opposed to obviously excluding a case of a שפופרת. shofopheret.
But that's because it is not touching the walls. והני מילי היכא
דשיע, v'hani mili heicha d'shiya, where it's smooth on the outside. אבל
פלוי פלוי, aval pluyei pluyei, if it has crevice cracks and some
of the blood is in those cracks and those the blood in
those cracks might be touching the walls of the canal, so in
that case טמאה. temei'ah. I don't care that it's that it's carried
by this chunk, she's still
טמאה. temei'ah. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? בשרה קרינא ביה. b'sarah k'reina bei.
It's touching the walls of the canal.
Right? Do you understand the point? If you've got your vaginal canal
here and you've got this mass, right, if all of the blood
is in here, it's not touching the walls. But if there are
cracks, right, and some of the blood is in the cracks here
and this is rubbing up against the wall, then the blood is
actually touching the wall.
It wouldn't make a difference where the blood came from. Well no
because that's the point. The תנא קמא Tanna Kama says, I'm going
to assume this is נידה niddah blood. Okay and but what I
will say that there's a concern about whether it's touching the walls
or not. So in a case where it did touch the wall,
even if it came from the mass, you know even though it
was inside the mass and came out of those cracks, he says
I'm assuming it's נידה niddah blood, the only way I got you
off was by saying it wasn't touching the walls. So if it
came out of those cracks and touched the walls you'd be טמאה
temei'ah because that's his approach. It's about how whether it touched the
walls. ואתו רבנן למימר, v'ata Rabbanan l'meimar, then the Rabbis come along
and say: אף על גב דפלוי פלוי, af al gav de'pluyei pluyei,
that doesn't bother me. Even if it's coming through those cracks, אין
זה דם נידה אלא דם חתיכה. ein zeh dam niddah ella dam
chaticha. This is blood of the mass and not blood, that's what
they debate, and not נידה niddah blood. So here the גמרא Gemara
says you're right, in the case when it's totally inside they all
agree she's טהורה tehorah but there's a big difference of what the
approach is. Is it because of an idea that it has to
touch the walls of the vaginal canal or is it because we
assess that in this case it's not נידה niddah blood? And the
big difference is when it is the blood on the inside of
here and it does touch the wall. Then you then according to
one it's touching the wall טמאה, temei'ah, according to the other, no,
I'm asserting that this is not נידה niddah blood. Okay you could
imagine another case which is the שפופרת, shofopheret, where you know it's
נידה niddah blood, you know it's coming from the uterine from the
uterus, but it's being caught in the שפופרת. shofopheret. According to one
they would say okay,
once it's נידה niddah blood end of story, I don't need it
to touch the walls. And the other approach says I don't care
whether it's נידה niddah blood as long as it's not a process
touching the walls. So this is whether the strict, whether lenient, one
approach has the idea of that it always has to touch the
wall and the other approach has
the idea.
How do you know that it has to touch the walls? That's
from בבשרו. b'visara. I mean, but how does he know that it's
just
not touching?
All right, so they may have made a דרשה. Drasha. How do
you know any דרשה? Drasha? So let's take a look. So גמרא
Gemara says like this:
והדם
נדה בה תהיה טמאה, v'hadam nida ba'is tmeya, and now the גמרא
Gemara adds a second part: If it was נדה Nida blood, she
would be טמאה Tmeya if it went through those cracks. But you
know what? If it went through those cracks, she's טהורה Tehora because
it's not נדה Nida blood. But if you were dealing with נדה
Nida blood, that would be a problem even in the tube. So
one approach says it's got to touch the vaginal canal and
the other approach says I don't have that requirement, but I have
to know it's נדה Nida blood. And if it's coming from the
mass, it's not נדה Nida blood, but if it's coming from the
uterus and it's in a שופרת, Shoferes, it is נדה Nida blood.
So that seems to be that this is exactly a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. So let's see how the שופרת Shoferes is the tube?
שופרת Shoferes is the tube. So let's see how the גמרא, Gemara,
I mean, it seems to be a very good explanation of the
debate. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara says it's not necessarily the
case. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, בשופרת כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דטהורה. B'shoferes kuli alma lo pligi d'tehora. When it comes to
the שופרת, Shoferes, I would assert that everybody would say it's טהורה.
Tehora. Why? Because maybe everybody holds of this idea that it has
to touch the vaginal canal, which is important because now it's giving
us that as an exception to the laws and אביי Abaye is
asserting that everybody would agree to that criterion: it has to touch
the walls. כי פליגי בחתיכה, Ki pligi b'chaticha, they debate only the
special case of חתיכה. Chaticha. Why might that be a special case?
מר סבר דרכה של אשה לראות דם בחתיכה ומר סבר אין דרכה
של אשה לראות דם בחתיכה. Mar savar darka shel isha liros dam
b'chaticha umar savar ein darka shel isha liros dam b'chaticha. One says
it's a natural occurrence, the other says it's not. Now why should
that matter? There are three interpretations of the ראשונים Rishonim here, and
one of them makes a huge difference. I will tell you the
three interpretations. One is רש"י Rashi says here אין דרכה ein darka
means something completely different. What it means is that there's blood in
the cracks like we said before, and what they're really debating is,
and therefore the blood is touching the wall, what they're really debating
is: is this נדה Nida blood or is this the blood of
the mass? Okay, but that's a funny explanation because that's not the
phrase of whether it's natural or not natural, it's not the same
phrase we used before. תוספות Tosafot says no, we're talking that the
blood is totally inside the mass, no cracks. But remember before we
said that there could be a difference between a tube and a
mass. A tube is an unnatural body, a foreign body, a mass
is not. So maybe what they're saying is in a tube, this
would be the easiest read of this גמרא, Gemara, in a tube
everybody agrees she's טהורה. Tehora. That's a foreign body separating. But in
a mass, that's where they debate. Is a mass considered a foreign
body or not in order to be considered a separation between the
blood and the wall? Okay, but in principle if it is a
foreign body, then we would all agree.
And the question is just whether it's a דרך Derech of this
to have it?
Either whether that actually is natural or not natural or whether that
makes a difference. Okay, although the language sounds like the first. But
that's the easiest explanation. Tube is a separation, is a foreign mass
a separation? The third explanation is that of the רא"ש Rosh and
becomes extremely important in הלכה Halacha in cases you would not have
imagined. And he says no, here's the explanation: that the blood is
actually in the cracks, everybody is agreeing that it is actually נדה
Nida blood. It's in the cracks and it's נדה Nida blood. And
nevertheless, one opinion is saying that because the נדה Nida blood is
coming out in an unnatural way, being dragged by this mass, she
is not a נדה. Nida. The נדה Nida blood has to come
out naturally, not being dragged by something else.
Like sort of like a דם מכה. Dam maka. Even though there's
no מכה, Maka, it's the blood, but it's coming out in an
unnatural way. Remember I said that that was a possible read before,
the גמרא Gemara introduced this idea of דרכה. darka. Maybe the whole
point of שופרת Shoferes is not about separation, maybe the idea of
שופרת Shoferes is unnatural. And now if we can say unnatural, now
we can say that she's not a נדה. Nida. This is extremely
important because it goes to, as Michael said, the issue of מכה.
Maka. Women have certain medical conditions and it's if it's מכה, Maka,
great, but sometimes it's not a מכה Maka and it still causes
the blood to come out. And it's uterine blood. Would that make
her a נדה Nida or not? So for example, a case that's
heavily debated is a case of I mentioned, I think I mentioned
this before,
uterine fibroids in the uterus. Fibroids are like little finger-like protrusions that
come up and the uterine lining goes around them. It's not a
מכה, Maka, there's no cut. But because of because they sort of
irritate, sometimes it causes some sloughing off of the cycle of the
uterine lining. So it's uterine lining coming out, normally we say אפילו
מחמת אונס, afillu machmas ones, even through some external reason. Or do
we say, no, we say that this is coming because of some
sort of something different inside of her body that's irritating and causing
it, like אין דרכה של אשה לראות דם ein darka shel isha
liros dam this way? Now that seems pretty radical from this whole
גמרא Gemara that's talking about a tube, but there are some פוסקים
Poskim that say that. The ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer tries to use
this גמרא Gemara to argue that. And this idea starts with the
רא"ש. Rosh. This תוספות הרא"ש Tosafot HaRosh here, if you look back
on דף כ"א עמוד ב', Daf chaf aleph amud beis, he develops
this idea, and he says I'll get you to the punchline. If
you're
three lines from the bottom of this תוספות Tosafos הרא״ש *Tosafos HaRosh*,
like almost at the end, like a third from the end, רבנן
סברי דטעמא דשופרת *Rabbanan savri detama dishofares*, the reason of שופרת *shofares*
is not because of חציצה chatzitzah, *chatzitzah*, but why? משום שאין דרכה
של אשה לראות כדרך כח *mishum she-ein darchah shel isha lir'os kederach
kach*. That's unnatural. וכן בחתיכה נמי *v'chein bachatticha nami*, even if it's
got these crevices and even if it's דם נדה niddah. *dam niddah*,
they said that before. You could check. לפי שאין דרך נשים לראות
כך *lefi she-ein derech nashim lir'os kach*. That's just not the natural
way for דם נדה niddah, *dam niddah* to come out. והאי דאמר
אין In, זה דם נדה niddah, התם קאמר אין In, דם נדה
niddah, רגיל לבוא בזה הענין *ve-hai d'ka-amar ein zeh dam niddah hatam
ka-amar ein dam niddah ragil lavo b'zeh ha-inyan*. Therefore that's not the
normal way נדה nidda *niddah* blood comes out. וכן עשה מעשה השר
מקוצי *v'chein asah ma'aseh ha-Sar mi-Kotzi*, which is one of the בעלי
תוספות Tosafos *Ba'alei Tosafos* called the שר מקוצי *Sar mi-Kotzi*, באשה שנעקר
מקור שלה *b'isha she-ne'ekar makor shelah*,
that her uterus got uprooted literally. What it means is there's actually
a condition called a prolapsed uterus where the uterus actually falls into
the, part of the uterus actually collapses into the vaginal canal. Okay,
this was a big issue in the ראשונים *Rishonim* and the אחרונים
*Acharonim*, how to deal with this case. Okay, and actually there's not
a מכה maka, *makkah*, there's not a tear, but now blood is
coming from the uterus in a very unnatural way. כיש נדה niddah,
*k'eish niddah* or not. So he says, וכמין חתיכת בשר נפלה בבית
החיצון *u-ch'min chattichas basar naflah b'veis hachitzon*, like a chunk of meat
fell into the vaginal canal. Now it wasn't a chunk, it really
was, they didn't know, but it really was actually the head of
the uterus had actually, I mean maybe he did, that's the way
he's describing it, had collapsed into the vaginal canal. ולא הייתה פוסקת
לראות כל זמן כל זמן שהחתיכה בבית החיצון *v'lo haysah posekes lir'os
kol zman
kol zman she-hachatticha b'veis hachitzon*, and she was constantly bleeding. והתירה לבעלה
*v'hittirah l'ba'alah*, he said she's not a נדה niddah? *niddah*, she's טהורה
tehora. *tehorah*, כיון שאין דרך נשים לראות כן *keivan she-ein derech nashim
lir'os kein*, because that is not a natural way of a woman
bleeding, having a menstrual bleeding. So this idea, which starts with being
this bizarre case of a tube and separation because the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* introduces the language of דרכה *darchah*, it's possible that it becomes
a basis in הלכה halachah? *Halachah* for a very
important medical condition, of saying if it's not natural, maybe that's a
basis. Now as I said, these issues are heavily debated whether you
rule like this ראש Rosh, *Rosh*, what is the scope, what are
the parameters? But still this is a very critical גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
for those discussions. Okay, one last point about how to read this
and then we'll go on to a new topic. רבא אמר דכולי
עלמא אין דרכה של אשה *Rava amar d'chulei alma ein darchah shel
isha*, three lines again from the top of כ״ב ע״ב *chaf bais
amud aleph*. רבא *Rava* says you know what, everybody could say אין
דרכה לראות דם בחתיכה *ein darchah lir'os dam bachatticha*, that that's not
considered natural or whatever and it's like the tube and the woman
is not טמאה tmeah. *temeiah*, whether it comes out in the tube
or whether it comes out
in the mass, the woman is not טמאה tmea. *temeiah*. והכא באשה
טהורה tehora, ומקור מקומה טמא tamei, קמיפלגי *v'hacha b'isha tehorah u-makor mekomo
tamei kamiflagi*. We're not debating the woman. The woman is טהורה *tehorah*.
The question is what do you say about the blood? Remember we
had this discussion before. Not טמאה tmea. *tameiah* her נדה niddah. *niddah*,
but if somebody touched the
blood would that person be טמא tamei *tamei*? Or תרומה *Terumah* touched
the blood, would they be טמא tamei *tamei*? She's not a נדה
niddah *niddah*, but do we say that blood that was in the
uterus even if somehow it came out in a way that she's
not a נדה niddah, *niddah*, maybe because the blood came from the
uterus the blood is טמא tamei *tamei*? מקור מקומו טמא tamei *Makor
mekomo tamei*, do we say that its source, its place, just being
there makes the blood טמא tamei *tamei*? As we said a sort
of a troubling idea, but this is a concept the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has, maybe that and therefore a woman could, the blood could
be טמא tamei. *tamei* without the woman being a נדה niddah *niddah*
and that's the debate. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. סבר אשה טהורה ודם
טמא tamei דאתי דרך מקור
*Rabbi Eliezer savar isha tehorah v'dam tamei d'asi derech makor*. רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* would say okay, the woman is טהורה *tehorah*, but all
he said was was that she's טהורה *tehorah* because it has to
come out by touching the vaginal canal, but the blood itself is
נדה niddah. *niddah* blood and it was in the uterus and therefore
the blood is טמא tamei, *tamei* even though she's טהורה *tehorah*. ורבנן
סברי אשה טהורה ומקור מקומו טהור *v'Rabbanan savri isha tehorah u-makor mekomo
tahor*.
No, the rabbis say when they say אין זה דם נדה niddah
אלא דם חתיכה *ein zeh dam niddah ela dam chattichas*, what
they mean is this blood
could be like any blood, like blood of a wound. The fact
that it came from the uterus doesn't matter. Once it's not going
to make her
a נדה niddah *niddah*, it's not going to have any status in
itself. And the debate would just be whether or not it would
make her a נדה niddah *niddah*, whether or not it would be
טמא tamei *tamei* even though she's not.
So the important point is that while
the simple read of the debate earlier was do we agree to
this הלכה halacha *Halachah* of tube or blood in a mass, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, maybe everybody says that blood in a
tube is טהור *tahor* and they have different ways of reading the
debate, which comes out to a lenient conclusion, which means if that's
the emphasis of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, certainly if it comes out
in a tube it's טהור *tahor*. There seems to be no question
that that's the discussion. And then the question comes out well what
if it comes
out inside of a chunk?
Or what if it even comes out outside of the mass but
comes out in an unnatural way? The question that the תוספות Tosafos
הרא״ש *Tosafos HaRosh* has, which has very important implications להלכה *l'Halachah*. So
that is the issue about that which ties right back to our
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* about the mass and blood that might be inside
of the mass. If this piece, whatever you want to call it,
mass, chunk, is a potentially developing fetus then wouldn't it be logical
to have? No, so we're assuming that it's not. Well that might
be. So that's exactly the opinion that it's not דם נדה niddah,
*dam niddah*. I mean you're right, the idea that it's not דם
נדה *dam niddah* is without a doubt the most logical point here.
But the good thing is we didn't stop there because if we
stopped there we'd be limited to those cases where it's not דם
נדה *dam niddah* and here we actually develop a principle that even
when it is דם נדה *dam niddah*. Well, you know, a mass
could develop that's not a wound. It's not like a cut inside
of... I thought in the last case it was blood of the
outside being dragged out by this. No, so let's say it's uterine
blood, but I don't know, somehow like Michael says, somehow there was
an aborted fetus that's drawing out, but it's not enough to make
the woman טמאה tameia as a יולדת, yoledes, it's only in less
than forty days old or whatever. So somehow something is coming out
and it's dragging with it some uterine blood. Okay, so that could
be the scenario. She's not a יולדת yoledes because it's not forty
days developed and it's not... and the question is like the ראש,
Rosh at least in the ראש's case, he understands it's blood even
on the outside, would she be a נידה nida if it's being
dragged out? The גמרא's Gemara case is what if it's on the
inside or in, you know, and so on. Okay, so let's go
on. Okay, we don't have to worry about exactly what that science
was. The important point is the principles, and they are extremely relevant.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Now we're going to go
a little bit off the topic, direct topic, but you'll see it's
actually a parallel, which is asking: What about a similar discussion by
a man? So let's take a look. בעי מיניה רבה מרב הונא,
Ba'ei minei Rabbah mei-Rav Huna, רבה Rabbah asked רב הונא: Rav Huna:
הרואה קרי בקיסם מהו? Haro'eh keri b'kisam mahu? If a man saw
a seminal emission, which makes him טמא, tamei not an איסור issur
of sex like you have by נידה, nida, but makes him טמא
tamei for laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Let's say it came
out not naturally, but the same way we speak about the tube
catching the blood of a נידה. nida. Let's say a person stuck
a very small sliver into the hole of the penis and with
it removed seems pretty dangerous removed, okay, yes, and painful, removed some
semen. Would that make him טמא tamei. for seeing, having seminal emission?
It didn't... it wasn't expelled naturally by his body; it was taken
out of his body. Now again, it's not an issue as much
like before that it's... that it's separating between, you know, you know,
between the skin, anyway here it's not on the inside. You become
טמא tamei. only when it comes outside, but nevertheless it is coming
out in an unnatural way. By the way, that reinforces the idea
before that maybe part of the issue was not the חציצה, the
separation, but the unnatural aspect of it. So that's what we're now
asking about the man. Let's say it came out that way. So,
מהו? mahu? What's the הלכה? halacha ממנו, mimenu, אמר רחמנא, amar Rachmana,
when blood comes from him, עד דנפיק מבשרו, ad de-nafik mi-besaro, coming
out of his flesh, quite naturally, ולא בקיסם, v'lo b'kisam, not drawn
out by a sliver. או דלמא, o dilma, היי ממנו, hai mimenu,
עד שתצא טומאתו לחוץ. ad she-teitzei tumato l'chutz. No, all it means
is that it has to be expelled, come outside of him. Again,
exactly the opposite of a נידה. nida. A נידה nida is בבשרה,
bi-vesarah, in her flesh, even on the inside, even when it gets
into the vaginal canal, she's טמאה. tameia? And as we said, that's
the basis of all the בדיקה bedikah cloth. The man is ממנו;
mimenu; it has to go out from him. Only once it goes
out, ואפילו בקיסם נמי, va'afilu b'kisam nami, it doesn't matter how it
goes out, even if it's taken out by a, by a type
of a toothpick. So אמר ליה: amar lei: תיפוק ליה דעצמו אינו
מטמא אלא בחתימת פי אמה. teipokei lei di-atzmo eino metamei ela b'chasimas
pi-amah. So he didn't answer that question, he said, I'll answer like
indirectly, like, why does that matter? תיפוק ליה דעצמו אינו מטמא אלא
בחתימת פי אמה. teipokei lei di-atzmo eino metamei ela b'chasimas pi-amah. Maybe
we should it shouldn't matter, because even the man only becomes טמא
tamei. if there's enough semen to fill up the hole. I don't
know if there's a medical term for that hole, but anyway... anyway,
if there's enough semen to fill that hole, and therefore in this
case there's not enough, because that hole is partly being filled by
the... by the toothpick. Now... now that is so first of all,
the גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that that's the amount required.
תוספות Tosafos has a discussion where the גמרא Gemara learns that from
and why it takes it for granted. We won't worry about that.
But the other obvious question here is, is that who's to say
that that's all that was taken out, right? You could take out
a lot through a size half the size, but you could take
out twice as much, you know, through half the size and take
out the requisite amount. So, I'll get back to that in a
minute. Let's first see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the
גמרא Gemara says: Look, it's irrelevant. It's not going to have... be
enough to fill up the hole. So the גמרא Gemara says: למימרא
דנוגע הוה? l'meimra de-nogei'a hava? So the גמרא Gemara says: Oh wait,
so that sounds like you're thinking about the reason he's טמא tamei
because of touching, as opposed to רואה. ro'eh. I need to take
a step back and explain this term this concept. In a way,
I think you all understand it generally. I've been describing for, you
know, for since forever that there's two ways you could become טמא.
tamei One is that the source of the טומאה tumah is external
to you. You have a dead carcass of an animal, you have
a corpse, you touch the corpse, you contract it from the outside.
That's considered נוגע. nogei'a. You're not the source; something else is the
source. You contract it from that thing that's identified as the source.
The other is רואה. ro'eh. רואה ro'eh is a condition of something
that's occurred to your body, and like you've had a you've seen
something literally, but it means something has occurred to your body, and
that makes you the source. That makes you טמא tamei because you've
had this experience. So, a woman has had a flow of blood.
A man has had a seminal emission. A man has had a
flow of זיבות, zivus, of some type unnatural, you know, gonorrheal emission.
They are a רואה. ro'eh. because this experience for their body they
are the source. Now the problem with a בעל קרי, baal keri,
the question is the following. The or the תורה Torah clearly says
that קרי keri semen is an אב הטומאה av hatumah source of
טומאה. tumah. Now the תורה Torah also says that a person, a
man who had this you know this seminal emission is טמא, tamei
but interestingly he's not as טמא tamei as a זב zav or
as a נדה. Not only is it not seven days, you have
cases where like a woman let's say who has one bleed you
know bleeds once during her non-menstrual period is only טמא tamei. for
one day. So not only does a בעל קרי baal keri only
טמא tamei, for one day, but more than that he would not
make people טמא. tamei Right, he is not a... right, normally a
source of טומאה tumah could make a person or vessels טמא. tamei.
A בעל קרי baal keri can only make food טמא. tamei, So
he sounds like a ראשון. rishon. Okay, but the קרי keri itself
can make a person is an אב. av. So the logical conclusion
is that it's only the קרי keri that's טמא tamei. and the
man is טמא tamei, because he has touched it because when it
came out right it touched his body and that's why he's טמא
tamei. but not because he's a רואה, roeh, not because he has
a status, a personal status as a בעל קרי. baal keri. Really
he's טמא tamei, because he naturally just touches the semen but the
only thing that's טמא tamei is the semen not fundamentally him. That
would be a very natural conclusion. Let me just read to you
if I can find it quickly the פסוק pasuk that makes that
somewhat clear at least that he has a different status. It says
like this: So no it's not explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. Here's
what it says: ואיש כי תצא ממנו שכבת זרע ורחץ במים את
כל בשרו וטמא עד הערב. ve'ish ki teitzei mimenu shichvat zera verachatz
bamayim et kol besaro vetamei ad ha'arev. So he has one day
טומאה tumah as opposed to everybody else mentioned here that has seven
days. The idea of a woman bleeding one day not during her
cycle is one day is more rabbinic דרשה derasha it's not explicit.
But he clearly different that he's only one day. וכל בגד וכל
עור אשר יהיה עליו שכבת זרע וכבס במים וטמא עד הערב. vechol
beged vechol or asher yihyeh alav shichvat zera vechubas bamayim vetamei ad
ha'arev. Then it says: ואשה אשר ישכב איש אתה שכבת זרע ורחצו
במים וטמאו עד הערב. veisha asher yishkav ish otah shichvat zera verachatzu
vamayim vetameu ad ha'arev. If a woman sleeps with a man and
there's a seminal emission the woman becomes טמא. tamei So a clothes
that touches the semen is טמא, tamei. the woman that touches the
semen is טמא tamei. or that has sex and has you know
the man ejaculate in her and the man is טמא. So there
seems to be an idea here that it's about touching the semen.
And the הלכה halacha although not explicit in the פסוקים pesukim but
the way it's clear in הלכה halacha. that this man is has
a status of a ראשון. rishon. He does not make people or
garments טמא, he only makes food טמא. So the logical conclusion is
that he is a נוגע nogea not a רואה. roeh. He's contracting
it from the outside. However that's not necessarily clear because there's one
הלכה halacha again not explicit in the verses but חז"ל chazal understand
that see it as an issue of personal status. And that is
we read recently in the תורה Torah that you send the impure
people outside of the camp. Now the מצורע metzora sent outside of
three camps. The נדה, the זב zav and so on the זבה
zavah are sent outside of two camps which means outside of מחנה
לויה. machaneh leviyah. If it was nowadays it would be off of
הר הבית. har habayit. But somebody let's say who touches a corpse
for example even a corpse itself is allowed in מחנה לויה. machaneh
leviyah. משה Moshe carried the עצמות יוסף. atzmot Yosef. You just can't
go into מחנה שכינה. machaneh shechinah. So the only people that are
sent outside of two camps are not people that contract from the
outside but people that their personal status is טמא, רואה. roeh. Guess
where a בעל קרי baal keri is sent? Outside of two camps.
He is sent out together with the meaning sent out but he
can't come in to מחנה לויה. machaneh leviyah. He stays in his
מחנה ישראל machaneh Yisrael together with the נדה, the זב zav and
the זבה. zavah. So that indicates that it's about his personal status,
that he's a רואה. roeh. So this is a question the גמרא
Gemara really is has a very serious question. There are indications that
he's a רואה roeh personal status, indications that he's a נוגע. nogea.
What do you say? How do we understand a בעל קרי? baal
keri? You have a question? No. Okay. So גמרא Gemara now shifts
to that discussion. How does it shift to that discussion? Because it's
saying like this: Oh, you say you need a certain amount חסימת
פי האמה. chasimat pi ha'amah. You need it to fill up the
whole... that to me indicates that you're considering him a נוגע. nogea.
Why? Because whenever it's about personal status it doesn't matter the amount.
When a man is a זב, zav, when a woman is a
נדה, the tiniest drop of blood, the tiniest emission. When it's what?
No no no that's if it's a stain and you don't know
where it came from. When you actually see it coming from your
body the tiniest speck, the tiniest dot. So therefore when is the
time that we require a minimum amount? When it's something you're contracting
from the outside, a minimum amount of a corpse, a minimum amount
of a carcass you have to touch in order to become טמא.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying oh you say you need a
minimum amount that sounds to me like you're treating him as a
נוגע. nogea. So now we're sort of getting distracted from the question
about the toothpick and we're asking how do we understand what a
בעל קרי baal keri is. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: למימרא דנוגע הוי. lememra denogea havei. If
you think you need a minimum amount that's only because you're considering
it like this is a source of טומאה tumah is the semen
and therefore you need a minimum amount of that stuff for somebody
to contract it. אלא מעתה אל יסתרו בזיבה. ela me'atah al yisteru
bezivah. So if a man becomes a בעל קרי baal keri when
he's a זב... zav... A זב zav requires seven clean days, like
a woman who's a זבה zava requires seven clean days. If a
man during this seven clean these days has another emission, a זיבה
ziva emission, he has to start all over again. The same way
if a woman has bleeds during the seven clean days she starts
all over again. Now what if during these days he doesn't have
this unnatural penile emission which made him a זב, zav, this זיבות,
zivos, let's say what he has during these clean seven clean days
is a seminal emission. What does that do to his seven day
period as a זב? zav? You got the scenario, yeah? Okay, so
let's take a look. Why did we teach זאת תורת הזב ואשר
תצא ממנו שכבת זרע? Zot Torat haZav v'asher tetze mimenu shichvat zara?
Here's the תורה, Torah, right, and this actually פסוק, pasuk, just the
language of the פסוק pasuk actually does seem to indicate רואה. roeh.
This is the law of זב zav and the man who has
a seminal emission. That seems to say that it is something about
personal status, not just contracting from the outside. And let's see what
the דרשה drasha is. מה זיבה סותרת, Ma ziva soteret, the same
way some of this זיבות, zivos, this unnatural flow, destroys, meaning causes
the whole seven days to start again, אף שכבת זרע נמי סותר,
af shichvat zara nami soter, so if a man has a seminal
emission, it interferes with the seven days. So אמר ליה, amar leh,
סתירה היינו טעמא דסותר, stira hainu taama desoter, so his question was
like this: If it's not about personal status, if I went ahead,
if a נדה went ahead let's say and she touched a corpse
during her seven clean day period, it obviously would have absolutely no
relevance. It's about something about her personal status. So if this man
during his seven day clean period as a זב zav went and
touched some other semen, he's a doctor, he touched some other man's
semen, it obviously has no effect. So why should his own semen
have an effect if it's an idea of touching? Clearly if it
has an effect, it's not because we see it as something external,
it's because we see that it's about defining his own personal status.
So he says, look, that proves that it is about רואה, roeh,
about his personal status. And again, just the language of the פסוק
pasuk sounds like that, it's about, this is your status as a
person. So אמר ליה, amar leh, he said back to him, סתירה
היינו טעמא דסותר, stira hainu taama desoter, I'll tell you why it
causes, it affects the seven day period, לפי שאי אפשר בלא צחצוחי
זיבה. lefi she-i efshar belo tzichtzuchei ziva. He's a very, has a
very creative answer. He says if this man has this other type
of liquids in his body that's causing the unnatural emission, so we
would be concerned or we would assume that when he has a
seminal emission, some other drops of זיבה ziva are mixed up in
it. Okay, you got it? So he's really not טמא, it really
does, it's not because of the semen that it affects his seven
day period, it's because when that happens we assume there are other
drops of the problematic liquid of the זיבה ziva mixed up in
it. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא מעתה תסתור כל
זיין. Ela meiatta tistor kol zayin. If that's true, if the concern
is that there's real of the זיבה ziva liquid in it, so
then he should have to start all the seven days again when
he has a seminal emission. And we know that's not the הלכה.
halacha אלמה תניא, Alama tanya, why do we teach in a ברייתא:
braita: זאת תורת הזב Zot Torat haZav and comparing a זב zav
to somebody who has a seminal emission: מה זיבה סותרת אף שכבת
זרע סותרת, ma ziva soteret af shichvat zara soteret, the same way
this unnatural emission makes you start, interferes with the seven days, the
same is true by a seminal emission. So but then the ברייתא
braita goes on, that we quoted before, but here's how it goes
on: אי מה זיבה סותרת כל זיין אף שכבת זרע נמי סותרת
כל זיין, i ma ziva soteret kol zayin af shichvat zara nami
soteret kol zayin, maybe the same way if he has the unnatural
emission he has to start the seven days again, maybe the same
is true if he has this seminal emission in the middle of
the seven days. תלמוד לומר בה, Talmud lomar bah, לטמא בה, l'tama
bah, to be טמא with it, with the זיבה. ziva. בה, bah,
excuse me, I said the wrong, if with each one as it
according to its type. אין לך בה אלא מה שאמור בה. Ein
lecha bah ela ma she-amur bah. So its power to interfere with
the seven day period is corresponding to the טומאה tuma that it
creates. סותרת יום אחד. Soteret yom echad. So it only interferes with
one day. Meaning, if he has a זיבה ziva flow during the
seven days, so the same way זיבה ziva flow causes a seven
day טומאה, tuma, a זיבה ziva flow destroys the entire seven days.
If he has a what? Start all over again. If he has
a seminal emission during the seven days, so how much טומאה tuma
is created by seminal emission? One day. So that sort of says
this day can't count, but if you're in the, if you saw
that seminal emission on day three, so you day three is three
over, then the next day you don't count day three, but you
don't have to start over again. So he says, look, you're saying
if I say that it's because it's its own thing, you're a
בעל קרי, baal keri, it's a personal status, fine, it's a status
that interferes but doesn't interfere as much. But if it's because there's
actual זיבה ziva liquid mixed up in it, so then it should
be like you saw a זיבה, ziva, this זב zav flow and
therefore you should interfere with seven days, it should have to start
all over again. So אמר ליה, amar leh, he said back to
him, גזירת הכתוב היא, gezeirat hakatuv hi, it's a biblical decree. זיבה
גמורה דלא ערבא בשכבת זרע, Ziva gemura d'lo areva b'shichvat zara, if
the sort of emission is pure זיבה, ziva, pure like of this
unnatural emission, then סותרת כל שבעה, soteret kol shiva, then it interferes
with all seven and it starts again. צחצוחי זיבה דערבא בשכבת זרע,
Tzichtzuchei ziva d'areva b'shichvat zara, little droplets of זיבה ziva that is
mixed in with שכבת זרע, shichvat zara, is mixed in with semen,
and fundamentally... seminal emission with tiny little droplets of זיבה zivah there
that we're concerned might be present, לא סותרת אלא יום אחד, lo
soteres ela yom echad, so because that's fundamentally about זרע, zera, although
so the the זיבות zivus is powerful enough for one day but
not powerful enough for seven days. But it really has nothing to
do with the semen. The reason it interferes is because of the
drops of זיבה zivah in it. So we actually have a גמרא
Gemara that ends inconclusively about this question, about whether his status is
because he contracted it externally or and the and he really has
no personal status as a בעל קרי. baal keri. It's all about
touching it, and therefore really it shouldn't interfere with זיבה zivah except
for the idea that there may be little droplets mixed in. Or
whether he does have a personal status of a בעל קרי, baal
keri, it's about רואה, roeh, and what are the נפקא מינה? nafka
minas? Well, as we said, the fact that he has to be
sent out of מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah seems to indicate רואה, roeh,
but everybody agrees to that. The fact that he should be an
אב av and he has a ראשון rishon would indicate נוגע, noge'ah,
but every... so everybody agrees his הלכות halachas are a little hybrid.
So at the end of the day, what would be a case
where we're actually seeing it would matter according to this? Well, the
case in the גמרא Gemara that matters is do you need a
minimum amount of semen? If it's about רואה, roeh, even the tiniest
amount. If it's about touching, you need a minimum amount. We will
see later when we get to a הלכה halacha? about נדה, and
a woman who has sex and then semen is coming out of
her body, and that does... does that affect her seven-day period? When
semen comes out of her body, that this question will become very
relevant because again this question: is it seen as some type of
affecting your status or just something in terms of some externally contracted
טומאה? tumah? I'll say one last thing about this, which is I
raised the question before about why, you know, just because you're taking
it out with a toothpick should we assume there's not enough? Maybe
you take a lot out with the toothpick. So תוספות Tosafot says,
actually the גמרא's Gemara point there was not about the minimum amount.
So the גמרא's Gemara point there was was that if it is...
if it's about נוגע, noge'ah, then touching... when you contract טומאה tumah
from touching, it's only when it touches the... you know, the sort
of outer surface of your body. Like if something touched, you know,
your inner cheek or something, it would not make you
טמא unless it touched the outer surface of your body. So what
the... the question here is is: what would happen... and this way,
by the way, it's almost exactly parallel to the earlier discussion... what
would happen if the semen came out without touching any part of
the external surface of the person? Sort of like the blood coming
out without touching the vaginal canal. So that's what תוספות Tosafot, understood
to be the issue to be. Not that it says you need
a certain minimum amount, but what it's saying is: oh, if you're
taking it out that way, it's not touching the outer part part
of the man's body. Like if it comes out naturally, obviously it
goes all over. But if you're taking it out that way, it's
not actually... it's touching sort of the inside of, you know, sort
of the... whatever canal, whatever it's called, but it doesn't actually touch
the outer skin. So it shouldn't be a problem. And that's why
the answer is: oh, you think it's because of נוגע? noge'ah? I
don't think it's because it touches his skin, I think it's because
it comes out of him. Okay, so that is the way תוספות
understood the question, also creates parallels before. And by the way, I
should repeat, we have not concluded what is the story when it
comes out unnaturally. That the גמרא Gemara never got back around to
try to answer, although the... never got around to try to answer.
But if it's all about not touching the outer part of the
body, I mean, when a man sleeps with a woman, it's all...
it's all internal.
Okay, so we'll talk about that later. Yes, it's a very good
question. Talk about that later.
Yes. Like if you eat certain birds, you become... Yes, that's a
very good point. That is a special הלכה halacha that the... where
the eating makes you טמא. But that is... but that's... but that's...
but... but... yeah, but... and but that's also if you touch it,
it's the exact flip of the norm. Because if you touch it,
you don't become טמא. So there are some exceptions, but the general
rule is it has to touch the outer part of the body.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on, back to the main theme
of our משנה. Mishnah Says like this: בעי מיניה רב יוסף מרב
חנינא מרבי אליעזר. Ba'i minei Rav Yosef me'Rav Chanina me'Rabbi Eliezer. רב
יוסף בר חנינא Rav Yosef bar Chanina asked רבי אליעזר. דם יבש
מהו? Dam yavesh mahu? Let's say we discussed in our משנה Mishnah.
if you have little dried-up chunks, you know, put them into water
and see if they dissolve and then they're blood. But that assumes,
the גמרא's Gemara assuming here, that they came out as maybe, you
know, or they passed into the vaginal canal as liquid and they
got dried there. But what if actually it came out of the
uterus and it was already dried up? Would dried blood, when it
went in that critical moment from the uterus to the vaginal canal,
would that make the woman a נדה? So... so מהו? mahu? What's
the הלכה? כי יזוב זוב דמה אמר רחמנא Ki yazuv zov damah
amar rachamana when her blood flows, עד דמידיב טייב, ad de-mideiv t'a'eiv,
so until her blood... until it flows, לח אין יבש לא, lach
in yavesh lo, only liquid not dry? או דילמא האי כי יזוב
זוב דמה O dilma hai ki yazuv zov damah when her blood
flows, אורחא דמילתא, orcha de-milsa, that's describing what normally would happen, but
it's not a criteria. ולא... אפילו יבש נמי ve-lo... afilu yavesh nami
and even if it came out dry from the uterus to the
vaginal canal, she would also be a נדה. אמר ליה תניתוה. Amar
lei tanyituha. We taught it in... and... this is the משנה. mishna.
דם הנדה ובשר המת מטמאין לחים ויבשים. Dam haniddah u'v'sar ha-meis mitamin
lachin ve-yaveshin. Blood of a נדה and the flesh of a corpse.
Now again, this is not about the woman's status, if somebody touched
these things, does he or she contract טומאה tumah from them as
a source of טומאה? tumah? So they cause טומאה tumah whether liquid
or dried. אמר ליה לח ונעשה יבש לא קמיבעיא לי. Amar leh
lach venaaseh yavash lo kamibaya li. Starting as a liquid and then
becoming dry, which is implicit here like the flesh of the corpse,
right, it dried up. So that I have no question. Obviously, that
would be a problem. That's implicit in our משנה. mishna. כי מיבעיא
לי יבש מעיקרא. Ki mibaya li yavash meikara. What if it was
just dried from the original? By the way, that's also not so
relevant because that's not about making the woman a נדה, that's just
about the status of the blood. But anyway, he says that's not
relevant. Okay, הא נמי תניתוה. Ha nami tanitua. We also taught that.
That's implicit in our משנה. mishna. המפלת כמין קליפה, Hamapelet kemin klipa,
if a woman expels something that looks like a shell, כמין שערה
kemin saara or hair, כמין עפר kemin afar or like dust, כמין
יבחושים אדומים kemin yavchushim adumim or like little red gnats, תטיל למים,
tatil lamayim, you put it in water and you see whether it
was blood or not, dried up blood. Top of כ"ב עמוד ב',
kaf bet amud bet, אם נימוחו טמאה, im nimochu tmea, if it
dissolves she's טמאה. tameia. So you see even if it's dried up.
So he says, אי הכי בלא נימוחו נמי. Ei hachi bilo nimochu
nami. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, no, no, that can't be,
that dry itself being the problem because then it wouldn't need to
dissolve. Presumably the argument was that if it needs to dissolve, maybe
we're proving that it was once moist or whatever. But anyway, let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes. So okay, one minute, why do
you need it to dissolve? So there's an obvious answer. אמר רבה
כי לא נימוחו בריה בפני עצמה היא. Amar Rabba ki lo nimochu
berya bifnei atzmah hee. No, if it didn't dissolve, it's not blood,
like we've been talking now about chunks and masses and whatever. But
if it did dissolve, you see it's blood and it's blood that
was dried and it makes her טמאה. tameia So the גמרא Gemara
says, ומי איכא כי האי גוונא, Umi eika ki hai gavna, can
that really be that you have these little things coming out? Maybe
big chunks could come out, maybe those were aborted fetuses, but can
you have tiny little things coming out that are really not dried
blood? אין, yes. דתניא אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק שני מעשים העלה
אבא מטבעון ליבנה. Detanya amar Rabi Elazar bar Tzadok shnei maasim heela
Abba miTivon leYavneh. Two stories my father, רבי צדוק, Rabi Tzadok, brought
up from טבעון Tivon to יבנה. Yavneh. Remember יבנה Yavneh by the
way was the place where, what were they doing in יבנה Yavneh
other than having a בית דין? Beit Din? They were, anybody remember?
What was the thing? They set up their בית דין Beit Din
in יבנה, Yavneh, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin after the חורבן הבית churban habayit
and they asked for anybody that had any knowledge to come and
testify about, and even not תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim or anything, and
they collected everybody's testimony started to have about that. So he brought
up, presumably it means he came to deliver the following testimony, and
here's the testimony he delivered. מעשה באשה שהיתה מפלת כמין קליפות אדומות.
Maaseh beishah shehayta mapelet kemin klipot adumot. There was a story with
a woman that had these tiny little red things that look like
shells that were being expelled from her body. ובאו ושאלו את אבא,
uvau veshaalu et Abba, they asked my father. ואבא שאל לחכמים, veAbba
shaal lachachamim, and my father asked the חכמים. chachamim. וחכמים שאלו לרופאים,
vechachamim shaalu lerofim, and interestingly they asked the doctors. So very important
about the whole issue about using medical knowledge and trusting and consulting
with doctors. ואמרו להם, veamru lahem, and they said to them, presumably
the doctors said to the חכמים, chachamim, אשה זו מכה יש לה
בתוך מעיה. ishah zu makah yesh lah betoch meeha. Clearly this is
not natural blood or whatever, this clearly is she's had some type
of irritation, some type of a wound inside of her שממנה מפלת
כמין קליפות, shemimenah mapelet kemin klipot, it probably is causing these things
to come out. Don't worry, it's not uterine blood or נדה blood.
תטיל למים, Tatil lamayim, you know what you can do a test.
Put it into water. אם נימוחו טמאה, Im nimochu tmea, if it
dissolves you'll know that it is a problem. And if not, no.
Now that's a little funny because if they said it was a
מכה, maka, then you would think that even if it dissolves, it's
blood that's coming from a מכה, maka who cares? So I don't
really know the answer to that, right, maybe they thought that it
was a מכה maka that was causing chunks. If it was blood,
we would have to assume it was uterine. But maybe it's a
מכה maka that's causing little types of hairs or other types of
skin to come out and so on, not a מכה maka, that
blood is coming out from. But anyway the point is you see
that it could be expelling things that are not blood. Now we'll
just finish the story. ושוב מעשה באשה שהיתה מפלת, Veshuv maaseh beishah
shehayta mapelet, and an almost identical parallel second story. Another story with
a woman שהיתה מפלת כמין שערות אדומות, shehayta mapelet kemin saarot adumot,
that had like these little red hairs. Before it was the red
shells, here it's red hairs. So it's very interesting, paralleling what the
משנה. mishna You could imagine that our משנה mishna was a codification
of these stories, which is why our משנה mishna has the example
of shells and hairs because that was these stories. So red hairs,
ובא ושאל את אבא, uva veshaal et Abba, asked my father. ואבא
שאל לחכמים וחכמים לרופאים. veAbba shaal lachachamim vechachamim lerofim. So the sages
asked the doctors. ואמרו להם שומה יש לה בתוך מעיה. Veamru lahem
shuma yesh lah betoch meeha. So here they didn't describe it as
a מכה, a wound, but as a שומה, shuma, some type of
a growth. She has a growth. רש"י Rashi actually says it could
be a growth that maybe hairs are coming out from. I don't
know if it's at all ever possible for hairs to come inside
the body and growths inside the body, but whatever. That's what they
assumed, that it was something that maybe could be exuding these hair-like
things. But again the assumption being that if it was a growth,
it wouldn't have been blood that was coming out of it, but
some other type of thing that this could be, שממנה מפלת כמין
שערות אדומות, shemimenah mapelet kemin saarot adumot, it's causing these reddish hairs
to come out. תטיל למים, Tatil lamayim, put it in water. אם
נימוחו טמאה, im nimochu tmea, if it dissolves you have to, it's
blood and you have to at least be concerned that it might
be uterine blood. And if not, then she's okay. So anyway you
see the reason we do the test in the משנה Mishnah. is
to determine if it's blood. Otherwise, it might be some other thing,
some other, like we talked about before, mass. The גמרא Gemara maybe
didn't assume big mass could be a fetus, but this it didn't
assume you could have a tiny little mass that's not blood. אין,
yes, it's possible and therefore you have to determine it's blood. But
once you see it's blood, she's... even though it's dried. So that
answers our question, even dried blood makes a woman a נדה. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, I'm sorry,
we're not done, I keep on waiting, I keep on waiting to
get back to the answer, but anyway, okay, so anyway, let's, the
גמרא Gemara isn't done yet with the test. אמר ריש לקיש ובפושרין,
Amar Reish Lakish u'vephoshrin, in order to do the test, the water
has to be lukewarm. Can't be too cold, can't be too hot.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, תתנה למים ובפושרין,
tetneh lemayim u'vephoshrin, in water and in lukewarm water. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim
omrim, מעכה ברוק ועל גבי ציפורן, me'achah berok ve'al gabi tziporen, what
you do is you put a little spit on it and you
have it on your like fingernail and then who cares, we're talking
about the woman and what... we're no longer talking about a טומאת
טהרה tumat tahara concern about... we're talking about the woman, about the
נדה concern. And then you sort of and you try, you know,
you use your, you know, and you sort of smush it and
you see what and you see if it like flattens out and
you see if it sort of liquefies. מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaiehu, what's
the end, what would be a case, what's there... what are they
really arguing about? אמר רבינא מעוכה על ידי הדחק איכא בינייהו, Amar
Ravina me'uchah al yedei hadechak ika beinaiehu, what they're arguing about is,
you know, one says you just let it dissolve by itself, the
other says is you smush it. So maybe the first opinion would
say if you had to smush it for it to liquefy, then
it's not blood, only if it liquefies by itself. What? Why can't
you use hot water? Because presumably that also wouldn't, maybe it's a...
maybe that, again, if it's real blood, then maybe it's not blood,
but you don't want false positive. The question is how do you
do the test and not get a false positive? You don't want
a false negative, but you also don't want a false positive. So
the גמרא Gemara says, איכא בינייהו, ika beinaiehu, so מעוכה... me'uchah... איכא
בינייהו. ika beinaiehu. התם תנן, Hatam tnan, over there we taught by
a case of... we're still wrapping this up. Over there we taught
by a case of... remember the dried up blood of a נדה
and the dried up blood of a מת met that are מטמאין
לחים ואינם... metam'in lachim ve'einam... what was the הלכה over there? It
says they are... what we said before, excuse me, מטמאין לחים ויבשים,
metam'in lachim ve'yaveshim, hold on one moment, no, so there... let me...
let me just check רש''י. Rashi. Oh, right, right, I'm sorry, I'm
sorry. So the blood of a נדה and the... skin of a
corpse, the flesh of a corpse is even when they're dried up.
But there are other things that they... that they are still a
source of טומאה, tumah, but there are other things like a dead
rodent that only cause a source of טומאה tumah when it is
fresh. When it is shriveled and died and dried and desiccated, it
is no longer a source of טומאה. tumah. So how... what is
the degree of dried up that it no longer is a source
of טומאה? tumah? So there it says the following in the משנה.
Mishnah כמה היא שרייתן? Kamah hi sheriyatan? So it says what you
do is you put it in water and you see if they
become like, you know, if they become undesiccated, and that will be...
then it is not dried up and it still is a source
of טומאה. tumah. So how much do you sort of immerse them
in water? בפושרין מעת לעת. bephoshrin me'et le'et. It says it has
to be lukewarm and 24 hours. So that's over there. Now there's
to prove not what they are, but whether they're considered dried or
not. At what point are they so dried they're no longer a
source of טומאה? tumah? הכא מאי? Hacha mai? Here by the blood,
the question is to prove whether it's blood or something else. So
it says you have to put it in lukewarm water, but how
long? Does it have to be 24 hours or can you, you
know, how long do you have to run the test? מי בעינן
מעת לעת או לא? Mi bainan me'et le'et o lo? Do you
need 24 hours or not? שרץ ונבלה דאקושי Sheretz ve'neveilah de'akushi and
שרץ sheretz and then נבלה neveilah and the... the animal carcass that
have become hard, בעינן מעת לעת, bainan me'et le'et, you need 24
hours. אבל דם דרכיך לו, Aval dam derachich lo, blood is naturally...
also they start harder, blood is naturally softer. So maybe you don't
need 24 hours. או דילמא לא שנא, O dilma lo shana, maybe
it shouldn't matter, you always do a 24-hours תיקו teiku and it
doesn't answer. Now I actually gave a different answer... the גמרא's Gemara
distinction was about you start with something hard or something soft, how
much time do you need? But also the difference is what are
we trying to prove? And תוספות makes this point. By the שרץ
sheretz and the נבלה, neveilah, we know what they were. We're trying
to prove... determine whether their status is considered to be desiccated or
not and have they reached that level? By here we're trying to
do a test to determine if it's blood and maybe that test
is a different type of a test.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't know the answer. But also the גמרא
Gemara never really answered
the question of what if the blood comes out dried? Because in
the end it said it seems to have been felt satisfied that
from our משנה Mishnah where it talks about these dried chunks coming
out, it proves even if it came out dried. Although I pointed
out, you know, the משנה's Mishnah not clear because the משנה Mishna
says that those chunks come out of her body. You don't know
exactly what status they were when they went from the uterus to
the vaginal canal, but I guess you could never know that. And
therefore, right, unless, you know, how you gonna ever really know that?
So the גמרא Gemara seems to be satisfied that even if it
comes out dried, it still makes the woman a נדה, it doesn't
have to be flowing and liquid when it's coming from the uterus
to the vaginal canal. Even if you see this wasn't such a
common case, they didn't even know how long exactly. Okay, let's go,
we can still go a little bit further because the next גמרא
is actually quite straightforward. Now we start talking about what's the major
focus of this פרק, perek, which is how do you determine what
a fetus is? And it said that if it looks like a
fish or other types of things it's not a problem, if it
looks... it has to have a human... a human sort of appearance.
If it looks like an animal like a, you know, kosher or
non-kosher בהמה או חיה, beheimah o chaya, then it is a debate
whether that is considered... And we said the reason was because אי
אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם, ee efshar lifteechat hakever b'lo dam, whenever
a mass comes out it brings some blood, you know, it causes
the uterus to open and some blood comes out. So why didn't
he say that she's טמאה in this case of this like fish-like
fetus? Why didn't he say that even though she's not טמאה כילדת,
tameia k'yoledet, some blood must have come out because she aborted something
from her uterus? So the גמרא says אמר ריש לקיש במחלוקת שנויה,
Amar Reish Lakish b'machloket shnuya, you're right, it would be debated, רבנן
היא, rabbanan hee, the משנה is talking about the majority opinion. But
according to רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, when she aborts a fish-like fetus,
if her uterus opens then blood came out. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו
תימא רבי יהודה, V'Rebi Yochanan amar afillu teima Rebi Yehuda, even רבי
יהודה Rebi Yehuda עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה התם אלא גבי
חתיכה דעביד דם דקריש, ad kan lo ka'amar Rebi Yehuda hatam ella
gabi chaticha d'avid dam d'karish, that was the other approach of רבי
יהודה. Rebi Yehuda. The other approach of רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda was
not that the opening of the uterus causes blood to come out,
but that the actual mass itself was dried up blood. That's why
he said it. So this is exactly the two opinions of what
רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda was saying. התם גבי חתיכה, Hatam gabi chaticha,
there the blood could dry up and become a mass, אבל בריה
לא הוי, aval birya lo havai, something that actually looks like a
formed fetus, even though it looks like a fish or whatever, this
isn't blood, this is a fetus. So this is exactly the debate,
why did רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda say when the mass came out
she's טמאה? Is it because the mass was blood, or is it
because the opening of the uterus caused blood to come out? And
the difference would be when you know the mass is not blood.
You know that this is a fetus, not maybe halachically because it
doesn't have a human, a human form, but you know it's a
fetus. So if you say it's because he thought it was blood,
then she's טהורה. If it's because when something comes out blood comes
out, then she would be טמאה. So now the גמרא sort of
basically spells that out. ולאידך לישנא דאמר רבי יוחנן, U'l'idach lishna d'amar
Rebi Yochanan, but one minute, there's this is רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan
saying that it's about it being blood, but we have one opinion
that רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan himself said אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא
דם דפליגי, ee efshar lifteechat hakever b'lo dam d'pligi, that the whole
debate is about the opening of the uterus causes blood to come
out. So according to that, ליפלוג נמי רבי יהודה בהא, liflog nami
Rebi Yehuda b'ha, so even when if it's this fetus coming out,
he should say, you know, this fish-like fetus, that she's טמאה because
that would have caused blood to come out when it was expelled
by the uterus. גמרא says, you're right. מן דמתני האי לישנא, Man
d'matni hai lishna, if that's your version of רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan
that it's about the uterus opening, so here he would say what
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says. מתני הכי רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי
תרוייהו, Matni hachi Rebi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish d'amri tarvaihu, רבי יוחנן Rebi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish aren't arguing, they would both agree
במחלוקת שנויה ורבנן היא, b'machloket shnuya v'rabbanan hee, that when it says
that the woman who has this fish-like thing coming out is טהורה,
that's the rabbis who argue on רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, but רבי
יהודה Rebi Yehuda himself would say anything that's being expelled by the
uterus, it causes there to be דם נידה dam nidda to come
out with it. Now I have a very important tiny little תוספות,
because we skipped over a case. We had the case of the
little hairs coming out, and the גמרא didn't say, well something is
coming out, why don't we assume blood came out with them? Right?
Same question. Right? If little hairs are coming out of the uterus,
hair-like things, according to רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda why don't we say
blood has to come out with it? So look at this תוספות
ליפלוג נמי רבי יהודה בהא, Tosafot liflog nami Rebi Yehuda b'ha, אשערה
ובקליפה לא פריך. a'se'ara u'v'klipa lo parich. It didn't ask about the
case of the hairs and the shells, דליפלוג רבי יהודה, d'liflog Rebi
Yehuda, let רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda say that it came out of
the uterus so blood should come out. דמועטין נינהו, d'muatin ninhu, those
are very small, ולא שייך בהו פתיחת הקבר, v'lo shayach behu pe'teechat
hakever, they do not cause the opening of the uterus. It has
to be something large, which leads to רב משה'ס Rav Moshe's approach,
that if you have a very, you know, a small, like gynecological
instrument, that is very small in diameter, it's not a problem. It
has to be large to create a problem, even if you rule
like the נודע ביהודה Noda B'Yehuda when it comes from the outside,
and רב משה Rav Moshe concludes three-quarters of an inch in diameter,
which almost no gynecological instruments are, and makes almost the נודע ביהודה'ס
Noda B'Yehuda's approach moot, but this is very important because, you know,
it limits the scope of אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם. ee
efshar lifteechat hakever b'lo dam.